Hello friends, welcome to Tip Insights.
Today, in this video, we're going to discuss
what an OPD is and whether
our health insurance
card can be used in an OPD.
Many people have this question: can
we
avail of cashless treatment or reimbursement treatment on an OPD basis?
After purchasing a policy, the
first question that comes to their mind is whether it will be valid for admission
or on an OPD basis. What
happens is that many people do
n't know about this and they take their health
card with them to the hospital to use it in the OPD.
Many people are confused about whether
their card will be valid in the OPD or not. We're going to
clear all that confusion in this video today. So, let's
start the video
[music].
Whenever we purchase a health policy,
we don't know whether it will be
used in the OPD or the
IPD. This means that
it can be used even after seeing a doctor in the OPD.  Or it can be
used after being admitted to the hospital.
Neither the agent tells us this nor the
insurance company tells us this nor the
online portal from which we buy tells us. It is
written in the terms of the policy
but no one tells us verbally, so
many people remain confused. Many
people think that if we buy a health policy
then we can use our card in any way, we
can use it in OPD or IPD also,
but in this video I am going to talk about OPD.
OPD means
Out Patient Department, so what
happens in it is that when we have any normal disease
or any normal problem or
any health issue, then we
go to see a doctor in OPD, then first of all
we have to get a prescription
made there. Whenever we go inside the hospital, there are
doctors inside the OPD,
then we meet them regarding our normal
health issue, so we
take only this much treatment from them in OPD that
we take medicines for one day, two days or three days and go to
our home.  If
we do not get relief from those medicines and then
we call the doctor after three days or
we do not get relief from those medicines, then
in that case the doctor decides whether to
admit the patient or treat him in the OPD. In the
treatment
given in the OPD, they keep the patient for an hour or two hours at the most.
After that, they send the patient away after
giving him medicines or getting his tests done and after checking whatever
tests are there related to his health issue like
ultrasound or lab
tests, they give him medicines and
send him home. So what happens in that case?
Many people think
that if we have a health card, then we
can use it in the OPD as well.
But what is happening now is that some companies have
started OPD based treatment as well, which is
also available in the OPD. But some companies have
decided that some
companies are providing cashless treatment to the OPD as well
and some companies are also providing reverse treatment.
But what happens in that is that
earlier many companies did not provide it at all,
many companies  It does not allow the use of health card in OPD,
it
allows it to be used only in IPD cases. IPD means in
admitted cases. So, I am going to
make another video for you on IPD.
In this, I am going to tell you only about OPD. So, there are still
many policies
where the health card is not used in OPD,
it is only for IPD. So,
first of all, whenever you
buy a policy, find out this thing from your agent.
Secondly, you
can also read this thing in the terms of your policy whether
our health card will be valid in IPD
or OPD.
All the things are clearly mentioned in it. So,
whenever you get your treatment done through health
card, then you should know these things first.
If you still do
not know about this, then look at your
policy document in your mobile or in
your hard copy whichever you have received and
read it.
Get information about it so that you never face
such a problem in the future. If at the time of buying the policy in the beginning, even if you do
not know that
our card will be valid in OPD or IPD  If it
works then you can also find out by talking
to the helpline number of the insurance company or their toll free number
and they will
give you complete information.
Their toll free number is also written on your policy and their
email ID is also written, so you
can get information from there, but it is very important for
you to have knowledge about it
because whenever we have any
health issue, at that time we are
not able to decide whether our health card will be valid or
not. We feel that
our health card will be valid and on that basis we
go to the hospital for treatment,
so we should already know about this thing,
if you do not know then you
can find it out from your policy.
You can find it out by reading the terms and conditions of the policy. So that's all for
today's video, see you
in the next video. Till then,
hello, subscribe to our channel and
like the video. If you have any
questions in your mind, then
write to us in the comment section, we will
definitely answer it. So, see you in the next video, till then,
hello.